<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Paul's Covent-Garden upon Sunday the second of December, 1694 Being the day appointed by Their Majesties for a publick thanksgiving for the preservation of His Majesty from the dangers to which his royal person was exposed during his late expedition; and for his safe return to his people, and for the success of his forces by sea and land. Publish'd at the request of the parishioners. By John Swynfen, chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of Bradford, and lecturer at St. Magnus Church at the Bridge Foot. Imprimatur. Decemb. 14. 1694. C. Alston.</title>
            <author>Swynfen, John, 1662-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6289A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833122</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2065:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Paul's Covent-Garden upon Sunday the second of December, 1694 Being the day appointed by Their Majesties for a publick thanksgiving for the preservation of His Majesty from the dangers to which his royal person was exposed during his late expedition; and for his safe return to his people, and for the success of his forces by sea and land. Publish'd at the request of the parishioners. By John Swynfen, chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of Bradford, and lecturer at St. Magnus Church at the Bridge Foot. Imprimatur. Decemb. 14. 1694. C. Alston.</title>
                  <author>Swynfen, John, 1662-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Sam. Crouch, at the corner of Popes-Head-Alley next Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37597:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT St. PAUL'S COVENT-GARDEN Upon <hi>Sunday</hi> the Second of <hi>December,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>Being the Day Appointed by Their Majeſties FOR A Publick THANKSGIVING For the Preſervation of His Majeſty from the Dangers to which his Royal Perſon was expoſed during his late Expedition; and for his ſafe Return to his People, and for the Succeſs of his Forces by Sea and Land.</p>
            <p>Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of the Pariſhioners.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SWYNFEN,</hi> Chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Bradford,</hi> and Lecturer at St. <hi>Magnus</hi> Church at the Bridge Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Decemb.</hi> 14. 1694.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>C. Alſton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-Head-Alley</hi> next <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37597:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PARISHIONERS OF Covent-Garden.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE enſuing Diſcourſe was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with any Deſign to be made Publick, and therefore wanteth that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectneſs of Stile, and, perhaps too, that ſtrict Coherence of Reaſoning it ought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to have had. For which Reaſons I ought in Prudence to have contented my ſelf with that great Candor, wherewith you were pleaſed to receive it, and not to have run this needleſs Riſque of expoſing it to a more ſtrict Examination. But I was rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:37597:3"/> to Oblige you, by complying with your Requeſts in this particular, than be ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly careful for leſſer matters. And beſides the Deſign of it being truly Good, namely, to Vindicate the Providence of God, and to Aſſert its Influence in our late Happy Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, I would hope it may not be altogether uſeleſs. That it may obtain this End, is, and (by the Grace of God) always ſhall be the Hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your most Humble and Faithful Servant, <hi>JOHN SWYNFEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 3. line 3. for <hi>then</hi> read <hi>it.</hi> pag. 7. l. 7. for <hi>after</hi> read <hi>often.</hi> pag. 23. l. 3. read <hi>unexpected.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37597:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezekiel XX. 44.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ye ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I have wrought with you for my Name-ſake, not according to your wicked ways, nor according to your corrupt doings, O ye Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words having no great dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Context, to Diſcourſe thereupon would be wholly needleſs: You may take the ſenſe of them in this double Paraphraſe; Ye ſhall acknowledge my Deity and Providence, when, by freeing you from your preſent Slavery, I ſhall deſiſt from puniſhing you as your ſins have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Or elſe thus; The Deliverance from your <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, which I deſign to effect, is, not that you could lay any claim to it upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your Righteouſneſs, for alas, your ways are wicked, and your doings corrupt, but only for my own Name-ſake. The ſenſe is but little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried either ways, only the former ſhews what is the poſitive cauſe of their Deliverance, <hi>viz.</hi> the Holy Name of God; and the latter affirms that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37597:4"/> their Merit had no influence in procuring it: Either ways they afford theſe two Obſervations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That a very wicked People may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be delivered from great Calamities purely for God's own Name-ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That the End or Deſign of ſuch Deliverances is, that they who receive them ſhould acknowledge the Being and ſignal Providence of God therein. <hi>And ye ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I have wrought,</hi> &amp;c. This People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not only as wicked as any upon Earth, but had moreover Ingratitude as an extraordinary Circumſtance, which aggravated their Guilt beyond that of the whole World beſides; and their preſent Servitude in a Foreign and Barbarous Country had been ſo far from producing their Amendment, that it had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one ſin more, which they had newly learnt from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> namely, to <hi>make their Sons and Daughters to paſs through the fire to their Idols,</hi> as may be ſeen, <hi>ver.</hi> 31st. And yet as bad, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, and Idolatrous as they were, they are here aſſured not only that for God's Holy Name-ſake they ſhould be redeemed from their preſent Slavery, but that after they were ſo, they ſhould know that God was the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the firſt of theſe Propoſition is Paradoxical, that is, is oppoſite to the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Notions of Providence, and indeed to thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37597:4"/> Methods which God ſeems to have told us in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he will take with a wicked People, 'twill be neceſſary to be more particular in proving them.</p>
            <p>In Diſcourſing therefore upon the firſt, I ſhall firſt prove it true from Scripture. 2dly, Confirm it by producing ſome Inſtances when it may be to the Intereſt of God's Name to deliver a very ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful People from great Calamities. 3. I ſhall ſhew what Improvements ſuch a People are to make of ſuch Deliverances.</p>
            <p>And firſt, that a very ſinful People may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be delivered from great Calamities purely for God's Holy Name, appears from two paſſages in this Prophecy which affirm it. See <hi>ver.</hi> 9th. of this Chapter, <hi>But I wrought for my Name-ſake, that it ſhould not be polluted among the Heathen, with whom they were, but I made my ſelf known to them in bringing them forth out of the Land of Egypt:</hi> The place explains it ſelf, telling us, that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the wicked <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were Redeemed from their <hi>Egyptian</hi> Slavery, was <hi>for God's own Name-ſake.</hi> A like paſſage to this we have in <hi>Chap.</hi> 36. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>But I had pity for my Holy Name, which the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>had profaned among the Heathen, whither they went.</hi> Whether this ſpeaks of the ſame Deliverance from the Captivity in <hi>Babylon</hi> which the Text does, or of ſome other, is no matter, ſeeing it's plain 'tis here ſaid to be wrought purely out of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37597:5"/> 
               <hi>pity to God's own Name:</hi> Hence it is that in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prayers mentioned in Scripture, that were made for the Deliverance of a wicked People out of this or the other Extremity, this Motive is frequently uſed, that God would do it for his own Name-ſake; as in that, <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, for the Glory of thy Name, pity thy People, and Sheep of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</hi> From which Inſtances, and many more that might be produced, the thing appears to be true enough.</p>
            <p>So that the principal Matter will be to ſhew ſome Inſtances wherein God's Holy Name may be concerned to deliver even a very ſinful People out of great Calamities.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And here the firſt is, when the Doctrines and Worſhip of this People are Pure, Orthodox, and ſuch as are agreeable to the Rules of Chriſtianity; when their Faith and Diſcipline are both right, ſo that they make a very conſiderable part of the Viſible Church; and their depravedneſs in Morals is ſo far from being juſtified by the Principles they profeſs, that, on the contrary, nothing is more ſtrictly enjoyned by their Principles than Piety and uprightneſs of Life. Indeed this is the firſt, and moſt abſolutely neceſſary Ingredient to Intereſt the Name of God for the Deliverance of a wicked People. For as to thoſe who have either no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith or Worſhip at all, or ſo corrupt, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37597:5"/>
'tis as bad or worſe than none, ſo that they are neither parts of the Viſible nor Catholick Church; for ſuch as theſe, I ſay, to fall into the extreameſt Miſery, without any Deliverance from it, is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection at all upon God Almighty; ſeeing that he has never made any Covenant with or Promiſe to them that he will appear on their behalf; nay, he hath rather teſtified the contrary, namely, <hi>That he will pour out his wrath upon ſuch Heathen as know him not, and upon ſuch Families as call not on his Name.</hi> So that how far ſoever common Providence may be concerned upon account of their being Creatures, to free them from utter Miſery in this Life, 'tis very plain that his Holy Name is not at all intereſted in the matter.</p>
            <p>But now that it may be ſometimes concerned to deliver a Church or Nation, whoſe Faith, Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Worſhip are good and true, though the Practices of its Members are wicked, is equally plain too: For ſeeing ſuch Faith and Worſhip are conſiderable Duties, and muſt therefore ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe that have them amiable in the ſight of God, how can he evidence his Reſpect to them unleſs it be by ſome ſuch Temporal Deliverances? Beſides, if this Church be of large extent, utterly to eraſe it from the face of the Earth, is ſcarce conſiſtent with the Promiſes that are made of its Amplitude in the latter days, and that God will in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37597:6"/> all Places have ſome that ſhall fear and ſerve him; nay, ſuch ſevere proceedings againſt a People that retain ſo much of Religion as an Orthodox Faith and Regular Worſhip amount to, would Prejudice the reſt of the World againſt that true Faith which they profeſs; for ſeeing 'tis Natural, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, to judge of the Truth or Falſhood of any Religion by the good or bad Fortune its Profeſſors have in the World, like the <hi>Barbarians</hi> inſtantly concluding <hi>Paul</hi> to be an ill Man, when they ſaw the Poiſonous Viper on his Hand; where Men ſee the hard Fate of ſuch a People, they inſtantly conclude that the Religion they Profeſs cannot be good, ſeeing it could not ſave them from Ruine. In fine, by how much the ſounder Mens Religion is, ſo much the better do they expect to fare; and when Strangers ſee the hard Fate that hath befallen People of ſuch a Belief, they will be ſo far from eſpouſing it, that they'll think they cannot ſtand at too great a diſtance from it. So that as much as God's Holy Name is concerned to be reſpectful to Men of ſound Belief and Regular Worſhip, to Propagate the true Faith in all parts and corners of the Earth, and to make the Enemies to, to become Profeſſors of and in love with it, ſo much it may be concerned to deliver ſuch a People out of the Calamities into which they are fallen. And we are to obſerve, that this was that very thing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37597:6"/> which ſo long preſerved the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from utter Ruine. Though their Morals was corrupt even beyond Example, and their very Worſhip too frequently ſtained with Idolatry, yet in the other Subſtantial Principles, both of Faith and Diſcipline, they being ſtill ſound, though God Almighty for their ſins did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter reduce them to the very brink of Deſtruction, yet for the ſake of the other he did as often deliver them from falling into it. Hence when the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> makes Confeſſion of their Miſcarriages, and owns them to be ſo great, as to Merit an utter Extirpation, he adds this, <hi>Yet they are thy People, and Sheep of thy Paſture;</hi> and urges this as a Motive with God, that he would not utterly deſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When amongſt this wicked People there are a conſiderable number that are truly Good, then may the Holy Name of God be concerned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the Calamities into which they are fallen; eſpecially if the better ſort are like to ſuffer moſt, and thoſe that are more wicked may extricate themſelves; for, as God may think, why ſhould the Righteous ſuffer for the ſins of the Wicked? The Innocent bear the Puniſhment of the Guilty? Or good Men endure thoſe Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which they had no hand in procuring? This would be to ſeparate Guilt from Fault; and whereas
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37597:7"/> he himſelf has told us, that the Righteouſneſs of the Righteous ſhall be upon him, and the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Wicked ſhall be upon him, 'twould be to act counter and oppoſite thereto, eſpecially in the latter caſe, where bad Men eſcape, and the truly Pious only ſuffer: For this would expreſly verifie the Jewiſh Proverb, <hi>That the Fathers have eaten ſour Grapes, and the Childrens Teeth are ſet on edge;</hi> nay, it would be worſe than ſo, in as much as 'tis leſs Injuſtice to ſuffer for the Faults of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, than for thoſe we were never related to. Indeed if for Ten Righteous Perſons he would have ſaved <hi>Sodom,</hi> and that he profeſſeth he could not do what he deſigned whilſt <hi>Lot</hi> was in it; where there are an infinitely greater number of good People, we may reaſonably preſume he will not deſtroy the Country they live in for their ſake. And laſtly, if the Righteous ſhall not bear the Lot of the Wicked, nor bad Men eſcape, leaving the good to ſuffer in their ſtead, then thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities where the contrary to this would certainly happen, the Holy Name of God ſeems concerned to prevent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Holy Name of God ſeems concerned to deliver a Wicked People, that yet are of the true Religion, from utter Deſtruction, where the Eſtabliſhment of a much more Wicked People,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37597:7"/> and of a falſe Religion too, would be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of it: For this would be to change bad for worſe, to take away a little Evil, and introduce a greater; and like the Demoniack, of whom we read in the Goſpel, out of whom one Devil was caſt, and ſeven Devils worſe than the former en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into him. Seeing therefore that ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as theſe would be ſo far from leſſening, that they would abundantly propagate Irreligion, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and Sin, the Honour of God's Name ſeems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to avoid them. To this very Reaſon it may be are we of this Church and Nation obliged for that Deliverance which we this day gratefully Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate. Though with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Text, <hi>our ways are wicked, and our doings corrupt,</hi> ſo that we juſtly merit even an utter Extirpation; nay, though we publiſh our ſins as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and ſeem to vye with the Old World for all manner of Profaneneſs; ſo that to palliate or excuſe our Guilt, would not only much aggravate it, but likewiſe be the ready way to bring worſe Judgments on our Heads than thoſe we have already eſcaped; yet ſurely, compared with thoſe that muſt in all probability ſucceed us, 'twill not be criminal or aſſuming for once to make the <hi>Phariſee</hi>'s claim, thanking God that we are not ſo bad as they. At leaſt this we are ſure of, that no kind of Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are juſtified by the Rules of our Religion, as there are by the Rules of theirs. We maintain not,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37597:8"/> 
               <hi>That for the ſafety of a Man's Honour or Good Name, 'tis Lawful for him to kill or defame another;</hi> That <hi>in the caſe of Neceſſity we may juſtifiably ſteal;</hi> That <hi>Fornication is not evil in it ſelf;</hi> That <hi>if I aſſert or ſwear what is falſe, ſo that I mean not as I ſay, that I am neither guilty of Lying or Perjury;</hi> That <hi>'tis Lawful for a Servant, not having Wages anſwerable to his Labour, to cheat his Maſter, provided he can do it without his privity;</hi> That <hi>one Act of Faith and Love is ſufficient for a man's whole Life;</hi> And that <hi>Natural Attrition is enough in the Duty of Repentance.</hi> We hold not the Fertile Doctrines of Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, good Intents, keeping no Faith with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and that we may do evil that good may come of it. In ſhort, we have no Jeſuits Morals, no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Probability, nor any Point maintained, but what is purely Religious, Chriſtian, and Sacred; So that upon comparing the Principles of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> when one will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſuited to the ſtrict Rules of the Goſpel, the others are only raiſed up to ſerve the ends of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Policy, upon the Ruines of Morality, Society, and common Honeſty. And indeed in this reſpect, the badneſs of their Cauſe may be to our good, and the great Preſervative to keep us from Ruine. God Almighty perhaps ſees, that he will not, as we ſay, mend the matter, by exalting them upon the Ruine of us; nay, the Exchange will be to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37597:8"/> his own diſadvantage; and though he may gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his juſt Reſentments, by cutting off ſo wicked a People, yet that may ſeem to derogate from his Wiſdom and Holineſs, when it tends to the Eſtabliſhment of a much worſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When the utter Ruine of a People would involve other Churches and Countries, that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more Innocent, in the ſame Miſeries, then doth God's Holy Name ſeem concern'd to deliver them therefrom; eſpecially when a very conſiderable part of the World will be damag'd, and it may be that too where the purer Parts of the Church of Chriſt are. For here not only the Innocent will ſuffer for the Guilty, but Strangers miſcarry for the faults of thoſe whom they had no concern withal; nay, greater Deſolation will be cauſed in the Church of God, than is perhaps conſiſtent either with his Providence over, or tender reſpect to it. And this we may ſuppoſe another Foundation of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance which we now commemorate. Not to Remark the Civil Broils which our Ruine muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily produce in other Countries, what can we think would become of the Proteſtant Intereſt throughout <hi>Europe</hi> upon our miſcarriage? We may well ſuppoſe that the Common Champion for the Catholick Cauſe will uſe his utmoſt Endeavours to make it as Univerſal as his Empire becomes, his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37597:9"/> Conqueſts being but imperfect unleſs they make as great an Alteration in Religion as Government: And beſides the utter Ruine of the purer Parts of the Viſible Church, what Rapine, Blood, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery will needs be neceſſary in order to it? The Cruelties ſhewed to his own Subjects are but a faint Eſſay of thoſe Inhumane Barbarities that will be neceſſary in other Countries. What overthrowing Laws, deſtroying Conſtitutions? Violating all the Bounds of Humanity and Juſtice? How will Fire and Earth be mixed together? No difference put betwixt Sacred and Profane! And ſuch a Confuſion wrought in the beſt Parts of the World, as will but too ſadly repreſent the firſt rude, indigeſted Chaos, or the laſt, great, general Conflagration. Theſe things the Wiſdom of Almighty God may perhaps fore-ſee will be the Conſequences of our Ruine, and his Juſtice and Goodneſs ſeem concerned to prevent them. Hence hath his Almighty Arm ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, already in a very great meaſure, to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point our Enemies, and to deliver us. The kindneſs he bears to the Publick Peace and Good of the World, will not ſuffer him to permit that which would draw ſuch general Evils after it, and the Common Intereſt of Proteſtantiſm receiving its Fate from our Succeſs or Miſcarriage, ſtept in as an Advocate for our Preſervation.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37597:9"/>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe many Inſtances that might be produced wherein God's Holy Name may be concerned to deliver even a very ſinful People from great Calamities.</p>
            <p>From whence it appears, that no one can hence collect, that the Impunity of ſuch bad People doth at all argue that he either bears them any Reſpect, or that he is backward in inflicting thoſe Puniſhments upon them which they deſerve: Alas, 'tis only out of pity to his Holy Name that they are preſerved, and that becauſe greater diſhonour would redound to him by deſtroying than by ſaving them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Head, when I have added, that we muſt not either think that we are leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to God for our Deliverance, becauſe it might not be wrought for our ſakes, but for the ſake of God's own Name; or preſume that we may yet ſin with ſafety, ſeeing 'twill always be as much to the Intereſt of God's Name to preſerve us.</p>
            <p>For as to the former, 'tis well known that we for our ſins ſufficiently merited Deſtruction, and that if ſtrict Juſtice had had its current, there would have been no eſcaping it. So that whatever Motives God might have on his part, there could be none on ours. And yet even on his part, though other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions might concur, yet we all know that Mercy alone hath the moſt conſiderable aſcendant over Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in hindring its Execution. Or ſuppoſe it hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37597:10"/> not, why ſhould a Benefit be leſs valued, becauſe in giving it the Donor hath ſome reſpect to his own Commodity as well as to his to whom 'tis given? All that we are to look to, is, at the Benefit we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy by the good turn another doth us, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of our Obligation is wholly taken from hence, and not from any collateral end he might propoſe to himſelf in doing of it: And I think no Malefactor looks upon himſelf leſs obliged to the Government in ſaving his Life, though it doth, at the ſame time, deſign to employ him in the Wars.</p>
            <p>And then for the other, namely, our preſuming to ſin becauſe it will be as much, as it hitherto has, the Intereſt of God's Name to preſerve us from Ruine: This is, I ſay, as unreaſonable as the other; and that not only becauſe of the Ingratitude of it, as being an high Abuſe of his Goodneſs, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Grace into wantonneſs; but likewiſe for another, which is in this caſe a much weightier Reaſon, and that is</p>
            <p>The uncertainty of the Rule in general. For tho' God Almighty in all his Actions doth conſult the Honour of his Name, yet you muſt note, that he knows how more effectually to promote this, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by deſtroying than by ſaving a wicked People; in as much as in all ſuch Eminent Acts of Juſtice he highly declares his Reſentments of Sin, doth Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon Malefactors, and thereby makes himſelf
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37597:10"/> feared in the World; and tho' in ſuch Puniſhments all the forementioned Inſtances, in which God's Holy Name ſeems concerned for their prevention, may happen, and yet are taken no notice of, yet he knows how to recompence himſelf for theſe by an hundred other things that he can cauſe to happen. Thus he at laſt dealt with theſe very <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> after he had delivered them from time to time, from one Danger and another, and ſaw that nothing would bring them to a thorow Reformation, he utterly deprives them of their Native Country, City, and Temple; and after a Slaughter of innumerable Thouſands, makes them Vagrants upon the face of the Earth, without any ſetled place of abode. The ſame thing hath he ſince done to the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches, who, not obſerving the Cautions given them by St. <hi>John,</hi> are utterly waſted, and nothing but the Name of them at preſent continueth; ſo that now <hi>Seges ubi Troja fuit,</hi> and where the True God was once worſhipp'd, and Chriſtianity flouriſh'd in the greateſt ſplendour, nothing is to be found but the Moſques of Pagans, and <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Sacrifices alone obtain; ſuch Deſolations do the abuſed Mercies and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God ſometimes effect. Now, we are to obſerve, that amongſt both theſe People the True Religion was once eſtabliſhed, abundance of good People, there muſt undoubtedly be; a far worſe People and Religion too ſucceeded in their room,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37597:11"/> and a very great Breach, no doubt, was made by their Ruine upon the whole Church of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and yet we ſee what hath befallen them.</p>
            <p>So that I ſay, tho' for his own Name-ſake, God Almighty may ſometimes ſee fit to ſpare a very wicked People, yet ſeeing he can bring Good out of Evil, and Light out of Darkneſs; can turn thoſe Accidents that ſeem moſt againſt to be moſt for him, this is no ſafe Rule to be depended upon. He that can make the Deliverance of a People at one time turn to his Honour, can, at another time, make their Deſtruction contribute to the ſame End; and when his Patience is abuſed, the fore-mention'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhew that he will take other Methods.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid it appears, that the beſt Uſes we can make of any Deliverances that God Almighty may have vouchſafed us, are not only to give the Glory of them to his Holy Name, but to uſe our Endeavours by Repentance and a ſober Life, to continue this kindneſs of his to us. We cannot think that any thing but reſpect to his own Honour could ever put him upon appearing on the behalf of ſo wretched, ſo degenerate, and ſo profane a People. And bleſſed be his Holy Name, that it has intereſted it ſelf for our ſafety; that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>giving us a Cup of Trembling, making us</hi> Magor Miſſabibs, <hi>Terrors to thoſe that are round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us,</hi> he has made us a Joy, and a Comfort to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37597:11"/> our Friends, a Terrour to our Enemies, and lifted us up above thoſe that hated us. But let us not hereupon be <hi>ſecure or high minded, but fear;</hi> he that has raiſed us up, can for the ſelf ſame reaſons caſt us down. If we continue our Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, our furious Zeale, our cauſleſs Prejudice, our Murmurings, and the like; then I ſay the Intereſt of God's Name will be as much concerned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, as it hath hitherto been to ſave us: In fine, Unleſs we Repent we ſhall yet ſooner or later Periſh, and what hath been hitherto done in order to our Settlement, ſhall but tend to make our Fall the more Obſervable, more Surprizing and Afflicting to us, and more Grateful to our Enemies. I now come to the Second Obſervation raiſed from the words, which is,</p>
            <p>That the end or deſign of ſuch Deliverances is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2.</note> That they who receive them ſhould acknowledge the Being and Signal Providence of God to them therein; for the Prophet tells the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Text, that they ſhould know, that is, be convinced and fully ſatisfied, that God was the Lord, when notwithſtanding their notorious Wickedneſs, he had Delivered them from their preſent Babyloniſh Captivity. So <hi>v.</hi> 42. of this Chapter, <hi>And ye ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I ſhall bring you into the Land of Iſrael;</hi> that is, my reſtoring you again to your Native Countrey, ſhall amply convince you of my Being and Providence.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37597:12"/>
            <p>Seeing now that God doth expect this of us, with reſpect to all ſuch Deliverances, it may be ſuppoſed that in effecting them, he leaves ſuch Characters and Marks of his Hand and Providence, as are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to convince all obſerving and unprejudiced Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they are his doing. 'Twill be therefore neceſſary to enquire what theſe Characters and Marks are; that is, to obſerve ſome occurrents in the Deliverance of a Wicked People out of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as make it appear to be the Management and Handy-work of God. And here we are not to expect ſuch Proofs as amount to a Demonſtration; no, nor ſuch either as ſhall actually convince thoſe who have a mind to Cavil and ſearch for Evaſions. The former kind of Proofs belong to very few Articles that I know of, in the whole Body of Divinity, and as for the latter, they who have a Mind to be Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and are perhaps Diſſatisfied about the whole Doctrine of Providence in General, will be never Convinced but by Arguments of Senſe; and if by that, yet by nothing ſhort of what is truly Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: But 'twill be enough for my purpoſe, if there be ſuch Occurrences ſometimes happen, as are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to convince all obſerving and ſober-minded People, that they are indeed God Almighties doing: Such are</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the Deliverance is Miraculous, that is, when 'tis effected either without or contrary to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37597:12"/> means, or when the means that are uſed are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſproportionable to what they produce, ſo that tho they be improved to their utmoſt, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome other aſſiſtance, 'tis impoſſible but they ſhould fall ſhort of their end; for ſeeing there is in the World nothing but God and Nature, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Contingencies happen muſt be produced by one of them: If therefore a thing fall out, that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had no concern in producing or ſo little, that if left to its ſelf, it could by no means effect it; here's a plain Demonſtration that God alone muſt be the ſole Author of it in the former Senſe, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal in the latter.</p>
            <p>Hence ſuch Miraculous Occurrents have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſteemed an Infallible Argument, as well of the Exiſtence as Providence of a Deity; and where Men have ſeen an accident happen, either above the Power, without the Aſſiſtance, or contrary to the Courſe of Nature; they have never ſcrupled to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that the Hand of the Lord hath been remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in it. Where therefore any of theſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances attend the Deliverance of a Wicked People, they are ſo many <hi>ſignacula,</hi> Prints or Foot-ſteps of God's Handy-work and Providence.</p>
            <p>Now tho we believe that ſuch things are now ceaſed, ſo that whatever Deliverances happen in our days, means are always employ'd; yet even in them there are ſometimes ſuch Marks of God's Influence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37597:13"/> and Management, that none but the extreamly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced and wilfully Blind can fail of Diſcerning them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such are when thoſe very Men and Actions are the means and Inſtruments of it, which were deſigned for the expreſs contrary: I mean, when the Meaſures taken for our overthrow become the means of our Safety, and what was Deſigned to effect our Ruine, contributes to our Deliverance. For to bring this about 'tis plainly neceſſary, that ſomething ſuperior to what is againſt us do appear on our ſide. Now if all that Humane Power and Wiſdom can do be engaged for our Ruine, a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Wiſdom more then Humane muſt be Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to prevent it; and what I pray, ſhould this be but the Omnipotence and Omniſcience of God, the weakneſs of whom is ſtronger, and the fooliſhneſs of whom is wiſer then Men; At leaſt ſuppoſe thoſe that aim at the Ruine of a People, are by the ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of Affairs neceſſitated to take ſome falſe ſteps, in the doing of which they may very probably ſpoile their Deſign; yet who is it that puts them upon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king theſe impudent meaſures, but he that giveth ſuch men <hi>up to ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> evacuating their Counſels, and fruſtrating their Deſigns? Or Laſtly, which (conſidering the ſtate of things, is the more common caſe) ſuppoſe the Ruine of the Liberties or Religion of a People, be according to outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37597:13"/> unavoidable, ſo that to moſt Mens think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there needs little to effect it beſides a Potent Power, hardned Malice, unanimous Councels, and a vigorous Proſecution; where all theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, and yet the affair not only miſcarry, but with the utter Ruine too of the Contrivers, who can want ſenſe to perceive the Finger of the Lord in all this, eſpecially conſidering what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, That <hi>it is he who takes the wicked in the work of their own hands,</hi> that he brings it to paſs, that <hi>his wickedneſs ſhall fall on his own head, and his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent dealings on his own pate,</hi> and Laſtly, that <hi>he makes himſelf known by the Judgments he executes</hi> in ſo doing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the Means concerned in effecting the Deliverance are no ways proportionable to the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties they conquer, either with reſpect to the open Enemies they are to ſubdue, or to the inward Diſtractions of that People for whom 'tis procur'd; that is to ſay, when thoſe very People that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, are not only prepoſſeſſed againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance it ſelf, and the means uſed in procuring it, but likewiſe have an open Force engaged for their Ruine, much ſtronger than thoſe who appear for their Safety; this is, I ſay, another mark of God's doing and Providence: For if we conſider the two Bodies of outward Force ſeparately by themſelves, that is, one riſing againſt, and the other in behalf
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37597:14"/> of a People, Reaſon and common Experience tells us, that, where for Conduct, Valour, and the like, they are equal, that the ſtronger ſide ſhould get the Victory; eſpecially, where they are double or triple the Number, it cannot be deny'd: And therefore in the Inſtances we have in Scripture, of a leſſer Force conquering a greater, 'tis always attributed to the Providence of God, who is ſure to bring Succeſs to that ſide he doth eſpouſe. Much more when the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon whoſe account the Conteſt is undertaken, are not only prejudiced againſt their Deliverers, but againſt their Deſign too; then, I ſay, their Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſeems ſo far from being probable, that their utter Ruine ſeems unavoidable, and that becauſe this will not only diſcourage thoſe who have taken Arms in their Quarrel, but very much diſpoſe them to Differences among themſelves; either of which muſt needs prove fatal to them. So that for ſuch a People in ſuch Circumſtances, and by ſuch Means to be delivered, muſt needs afford an ample Proof of God's doing and Providence.</p>
            <p>I might to theſe add ſome other Inſtances of God's Providence in matters of this Nature; as where the Deliverance is ſeaſonable, coming in that very nick of time in which it was moſt wanted, and yet far from being expected, like the Deliverance of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Eſther,</hi> that when <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Deſigns were ripe for Execution, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37597:14"/> expected nothing but to fall a Sacrifice to his Malice, that God Almighty ſhould appear in the critical Minute for their unexped Safety and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. But I think we need neither this, nor any others. What our Saviour ſaid of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that if they would not regard the ordinary means of <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> the more extraordinary and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous <hi>of one coming from the Dead,</hi> would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them, may be ſaid here; that a Miraculous Deliverance would hardly convince ſuch People of its being done by God, whom ſuch wonderful, tho' but ordinary appearances as theſe will not ſatisfie. I think I need not ſcruple to ſay, that though the Judgments of God are ſometimes a great Deep, and his ways very unſearchable, yet in theſe and ſuch like, they are ſo manifeſt, that he that runs may read them. As 'tis <hi>God who Rules in the Armies of Men, pulls down one, and ſets up another,</hi> diſpoſes of States and Kingdoms as pleaſeth him; and in fine, to make himſelf known, ſometimes delivers a wicked People out of Extremity; ſo are we fully perſwaded, that he need not give greater Evidence of his doing and handy-work, than theſe here produced. In requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring therefore thoſe who receive them, to own and acknowledge him therein, is no unreaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; on the contrary, 'tis highly Rational, that when he ſo Remarkably ſignalizeth himſelf, that he ſhould be obſerved and taken notice of: For ſeeing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37597:15"/> they receive the benefit of it, why ſhould they not acknowledge its Author? Eſpecially when God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty doth ſo much inſiſt upon it, giving them to underſtand, that one of his main Ends is wholly loſt, where his Hand and Counſel are not taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of. I ſhall therefore endeavour to preſs this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you in two words, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, doth God Almighty make ſuch large Diſcoveries of his Being and Providence in ſome Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Deliverances even of wicked People? Then let our Faith be hereby more ſtrongly confirmed in the general belief of that his Being and Providence; that is, let us fully conclude not only that there is a God, but that he does likewiſe Rule and Reign in the World, when we obſerve inſtances of ſuch Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances as theſe are. We ſee 'tis this that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty doth particularly aim at in effecting them; and when the <hi>Iſraelit es</hi> Faith in theſe Articles hath begun to flag and grow weak immediately God hath ſet himſelf to work ſome ſuch grand occurrent, and thereby hath repaired and ſtrengthened it: And I can by no means ſee why the ſame things ſhould not have the ſame effects on us; that is, why De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances that have been wrought for us ſhould not amply confirm our belief both that God is, and that he governs the World! perhaps the reaſon may be, that there is not ſo much of Miracle in our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances as there ſometimes was in theirs; or that God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37597:15"/> Almighty doth not by an inſpired Prophet, or an Angel from Heaven tell us, that he will bring about ſuch a Deliverance for us, at ſuch a time, in ſuch a manner, and by ſuch Inſtruments, as he ſometimes told the <hi>Jews</hi> he would. But are there no inſtances of God's Handy-work but ſuch as are Miraculous? Or can he be concerned in no occurrent, becauſe he doth not tell us by an Angel's Mouth that he is ſo? Are there not rather rational Evidences of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which tho' not Miraculous, yet ſuch as are very convincing and ſatisfactory that God's Hand and Counſel is therein? One would almoſt conclude that there were no ſuch Evidences, when he reflects upon the intolerable Atheiſm and Infidelity of the preſent Age, with reſpect to all ſuch Occurrences: Inſtead of Religion's gaining Ground hereby, Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Profaneneſs have abundantly increaſed; and where ſuch things have been done as could be the contrivance of none, but of an All-Wiſe, Juſt, and Merciful God, Men have taken occaſion even from hence to become meer Scepticks and Atheiſts as to his Being and Providence. In this I particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the late Revolution, ſince which, if my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations fail not, Atheiſm and Irreligion have made a more conſiderable advance than ordinary; and, which one would think ſomething ſtrange, but yet 'tis what I have obſerved with ſome Reſentment and Conſerve, that ſuch Atheiſtical Notions and Practiſes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37597:16"/> have taken Foundation even from that very Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. If theſe did only ariſe in ſome tender, tho' weak Chriſtians, from their reflecting upon the great Wickedneſs of the Nation, and from thence taking Offence at the Deliverance, ſomething might be ſaid in order to reclaim them; and one need but ſhew that ſometime the Holy Name, Honour, and Glory of God, may be concerned for the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance even of ſuch a wicked People, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Scandal muſt needs ceaſe. But alas, their Atheiſm and Irreligion are founded upon other To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks, and are moſt Rampant in a quite different ſort of Men: But this I can only at preſent lament and bewail.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing God's Hand and Counſel hath ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably appeared in the late Deliverance of our King and Country, let us be perſwaded particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to own and acknowledge him therein. If we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not this Duty, and that with hearty ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and concern too, we make the worſt abuſe of it imaginable, becauſe our owning of it was, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Text, the great thing that gave Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the Deliverance: Beſides we hereby loſe the greateſt part of the Benefit we might enjoy by the Deliverance, and that is a confirmation of the Goodneſs and Bleſſing of God upon our ſelves and Country. For ſuch as theſe God Almighty may work one Deliverance after another, and have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37597:16"/> nought for his Requital, but Silence and Ingratitude. He may free them from the worſt of Miſeries, and inſtate them in the quiet Enjoyment of the greateſt Bleſſings, and yet be conn'd no Thanks for his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. And give me leave to add, that 'tis a ſad thing to obſerve how many we have of theſe even amongſt our ſelves. Though our Deliverance fall ſhort of none, and hath all the fore-mentioned Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters in it of God's Handy-work, yet how few are there who own and acknowledge it? Some from a wonted Blindneſs, and never looking farther than the meer ſurface of things; others from not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Circumſtances of it with Intenſiveneſs and Application of Mind; a third ſort from an Opinion they have imbibed of God's unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the World, and leaving all to ſecond Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and another ſort I fear there are, who from a Prejudice and Diſaffection to the thing it ſelf, look upon it as the doing of the <hi>Manichee</hi>'s Evil God, who is the Author of all Wickedneſs and Confuſion, rather than of him who doth nothing but what is truly good. In ſhort, ſome from one ground, and ſome from another, take ſo little notice of God's Hand and Influence therein, that they ſeem little or nothing to regard it. And thus, like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old, God doth great things for us, and we obſerve them not: And did not the Government (by Religiouſly appointing days of Faſting on the one hand, and of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37597:17"/> Thankſgiving on the other) declare its Sentiments in the matter, namely, that <hi>it was the Lord's doing,</hi> I know not how we ſhould avoid the National Guilt of not anſwering the End which God tells us he aims at therein; that is, <hi>that we ſhould know that he is the Lord.</hi> However for our part, ſeeing we have ſo good an Example and Authority too for our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of his Providence therein, let us not fail to imitate it: And ſeeing our owning this, is not the All that is expected from us, but a ſuitable Praiſe, Thankſgiving, and Gratitude, let us not be deficient in them neither. Now we know our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer let us be Thankful to him, and ſuitable to the Benefits we enjoy by the Deliverance, ſo let our Acknowledgments be; then will God Almighty return to us, and that it may be with an increaſe of Bleſſings: Then will he render our Fleets Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous, and our Armies Succeſsful; then will he put an end to the ſad and deplorable War abroad, and compoſe our unhappy Differences at home: And laſtly, then will he Preſerve to us our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigns, and with them our Religion, and all that is dear; and in ſo doing will purchaſe to himſelf from all good Proteſtants, and all true <hi>Engliſh-Men,</hi> all Honour, Glory, Power, and Praiſe Everlaſting.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37597:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
